Register of the Jacques M. Vergotti Papers, 1948-1991
Hoover Institution Archives
Jacques M. Vergotti Papers,
1948-1991
91043
Vergotti, Jacques M., 1915-
3 manuscript boxes 1.25 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, other writings, deposition, and correspondence, relating to King Michael, Romanian participation in World War II, the transition of Romania from monarchy to communist regime, and Romanian emigre affairs. Includes a dissertation on Swiss neutrality.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Michael I, King of Romania, 1921-; World War, 1939-1945--Romania.; Romania--Politics and government--1944-1989.; Romanians in foreign countries.; Romania--Court and courtiers.; World War, 1939-1945.; Romania.; Switzerland--Neutrality.; Switzerland.
Biographical Note
Jacques M. Vergotti was born in 1915. A Major in the Romanian Army, he served as aide to Michael I, King of Romania, between 1941-1947. He witnessed the last year of the Romanian monarchy and the palace coup of December 30, 1947, when the King was overthrown and the Popular Republic of Romania was proclaimed. He was one of the few people allowed to leave the country together with the King, whose aide he was for one more year. He then emigrated to the US and has lived there since.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists mainly of his writings, particularly his memoirs, related to the dramatic events preceding and following the king's forced abdication. Also of special interest is his correspondence with the King of Romania, and with his colleagues and friends from the Royal Court, including prominent figures like General Petre Lazar and Mircea Ionnitiu, both friends and secretaries of the King.
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1985. (Box No. 1.)
  Consists of Vergotti's legal deposition as a witness in the civil action pursued by the Socialist Republic of Romania against Kimbell Art Foundation, regarding three "El Greco" paintings, 1985
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1948-1990. (Box No. 1.)
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1952-1991. (Box No. 1-2.)
  Memoirs, radio broadcasts, lectures, term paper, M.A. and Ph.D. dissertations, and miscellaneous typewritten writings arranged chronologically by title
- SUBJECT FILE, 1949-1990. (Box No. 3.)
  Includes King Michael's speeches and correspondence, correspondence by others, newspaper articles, biographical notices, obituaries, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by subject, and related mainly to the Romanian National Committee, the American-Romanian Academy of Arts and Sciences, the Carol I Foundation, and Romanian émigrés
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1985
  - Consists of Vergotti's legal deposition as a witness in the civil action pursued by the Socialist Republic of Romania against Kimbell Art Foundation, regarding three "El Greco" paintings, 1985 (Box 1., Folder 1)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1948-1990
  - Unidentified, 1952 (Box 1., Folder 2)
  - Balaban, Julian, 1979-1981 (Folder 3)
  - Ciorba, Ionel, 1950 (Folder 4)
  - Ionnitiu, Mircea, 1978-1990 (Folder 5-6)
  - Michael I, King of Romania, 1952-1985 (Folder 7)
  - Petre-Lazar, Constantin, General, 1950-1974. Includes his typescript entitled "Mortal Peace or Liberating War?" (Folder 8-9)
  - Willys-Overland Motors, Inc., 1948 (Folder 10)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1952-1991
  - "Swiss Neutrality"
    - Term Paper, Columbia University, New York, 1952 (Box 1., Folder 11)
    - M.A. dissertation, Columbia University, New (Folder 12)
    - York, 1952 May. Typescript
    - Ph.D. dissertation, University of Lausanne, Switzerland, 1954
      - Typescript, including attached typescript of oral presentation of the dissertation (Folder 13)
      - Printed copy (Folder 14)
  - "China: P.R.C. - Retrospective on a 1981 Study Tour," Sacred Heart University, Fairfield, Connecticut,1982(?). Typescript (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - "A World War II Profile: General Ion Antonescu," lecture, Congress of the American Romanian Academy of Arts and Science, San Francisco, 1985. Typescript (Folder 2)
  - "Reflections on Romania in World War Two According to the Diary of X. Xeni and the Swiss Press," lecture, Congress of the American Romanian Academy of Arts and Science, Paris, 1987. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Bassarabia [Bessarabia]: Crossroads of the Big Powers' Drives," lecture, Juliu Maniu Foundation, 1988. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - " 1948-1949: A Year in the Service of King Michael in Exile," lecture, Congress of the American Romanian Academy of Arts and Science, Los Angeles, 1989. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - Untitled radio broadcast commemorating the 23rd of August event, Radio Free Europe, 1990. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - "Memoirs of a Romanian-American 1940-1990," 1991(?). Typescript
    - Romanian original (Folder 7-8)
    - English translation (Folder 9-10)
  - "In Slujba Casei Regale," interview, Lumea Libera, 1991
    - April 20 (Folder 11)
    - April 27 (Folder 12)
    - May 4 (Folder 13)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1949-1990.
  King Michael's speeches and correspondence, correspondence by others, newspaper articles, biographical notices, obituaries, and miscellaneous material
  - American Romanian Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1985-1988. Includes a typescript entitled "Nicolae Radescu and Grigore Niculescu-Buzesti: Two Forgotten Men" (by Vergotti?) (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - Carol I Foundation, 1951-1978 (Folder 2)
  - Ionnitiu, Mircea, 1955-1990. Articles, writings, correspondence, obituaries (Folder 3)
  - Maniu, Iuliu, 1987 (Folder 4)
  - Michael I, King of Romania. Includes three of his speeches, 1950-1951 (Folder 5)
  - Romanian National Committee, 1949-1953. Includes correspondence between the President of the Committee and King Michael (Folder 6)
  - Romanians in foreign countries. Biographical note on Pierre Sergesco and miscellany relating mostly to Romania (Folder 7)